{"tossups": [{"question": "One of these structures named for Alexander the Great is known for its red color and found near Gorgon. After the Battle of the Allia, one of these structures was built and named for Servius Tullius; that structure was surpassed by the Aurelian line, built in the 3rd century AD. For ten points, name this type of defensive structure that was built by the Qin Dynasty to guard the northern border of China.", "answer": "<b> wall</b>s (accept Great<b> Wall</b> of Gorgon; accept Servian<b> Wall</b>s; accept Aurelian<b> Wall</b>s; accept Great<b> Wall</b> of China; prompt on descriptions of defensive barriers; do not prompt on fort)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "After dropping out of Reed College, this man audited a calligraphy class that inspired the \u201cmultiple typefaces\u201d of one of his products. A Walter Isaacson biography of this man inspired a 2015 film in which Seth Rogen plays a colleague of this man, Steve Wozniak. After this man was kicked off the Lisa project, he led the Macintosh project until resigning from the company he co-founded in 1976. For ten points, name this business icon and longtime CEO of Apple.", "answer": "Steve<b> Jobs</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "A palace partially named for this color was the residence of British monarchs for most of the 16th and 17th centuries. William Adelin died in a disaster named after a ship of this color. The Ditchley Portrait shows Queen Elizabeth wearing an outfit of this color. A rose of this color was used to symbolize the House of York, as opposed to the red rose used by the House of Lancaster. For ten points, name this color of the chalk-laden Cliffs of Dover.", "answer": "<b> white</b> (accept<b> White</b>hall Palace,<b> White</b> Ship Disaster,<b> white</b> rose,<b> White</b> Cliffs of Dover)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s Special Field Order Number 15 provided for the confiscation of land along the Atlantic coast to be allotted among freed slaves, which became the basis for the saying \u201cForty Acres and a Mule.\u201dThis commander presented 25,000 bales of cotton to Abraham Lincoln as a Christmas gift when he captured Savannah in December 1864, the culmination of a campaign of total war. For ten points, name this Union general who captured Atlanta to begin his \u201cMarch to the Sea.\u201d", "answer": "William Tecumseh<b> Sherman</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Two of these figures, Mushka and Pchyolka, were purposely killed in 1960 to prevent foreign powers from inspecting their vehicle. Strelka, another of these figures, gave birth to a child named Pushinka who was given as a gift to John F. Kennedy in 1961. The most famous of these animals was locked in a box for weeks of training and died of overheating after a separation failure, having completed four orbits aboard <em>Sputnik 2</em>. Laika was one of, for ten points, what trained animal cosmonauts?", "answer": "Soviet<b> space dogs</b> (accept descriptive answers of \u201cthe<b> dog</b>s that the USSR launched into <b>space</b>; prompt on partial answers, such as \u201cdog\u201d or \u201cSoviets\u201d or \u201cRussians\u201d or \u201ccosmonaut\u201d or \u201castronaut\u201d) (8) Laryngeal examples of these constructs are generally not found within the English language. The dropping of the voiceless glottal fricative type of these constructs took place during the 13th century. The place and manner of articulation are typically both given when categorizing these constructs, which differ from a similar construct in that they require a complete or partial closure of the vocal tract. For ten points, name these linguistic constructs that are often contrasted with vowels. ANSWER:<b> consonant</b>s", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Anthropology"}, {"question": "A group of people protesting Dick Wilson\u2019s corruption occupied this site under the direction of Russell Means in 1973. Stephen Vincent Benet\u2019s poem \u201cAmerican Names\u201d references this location, noting \u201cI shall not be there. I shall rise and pass. Bury my heart at\u201d this location. This site in the Pine Ridge Indian Reservation was the location of a violent episode when Black Coyote refused to surrender his rifle to U.S. troops. For ten points, name this site of an 1890 massacre of Lakota Sioux.", "answer": "<b> Wounded Knee</b> (accept Bury My Heart at<b> Wounded Knee</b>; accept<b> Wounded Knee </b>Massacre; prompt on Pine Ridge Reservation before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This cause was supported by Horace Greeley\u2019s pamphlet \u201cPrayer of Twenty Millions,\u201d which urged enforcement of the Confiscation Acts. People who proposed secession and opposed this cause were called Fire-Eaters. William Lloyd Garrison burned a copy of the Constitution because it failed to support this cause, which he advocated for in<em> The Liberator</em>. For ten points, name this cause that was achieved via the 13th Amendment and the Emancipation Proclamation.", "answer": "<b> abolition</b> of slavery (accept word forms; accept any answers related to<b> freeing slaves</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Charles Lennox Richardson died after a holder of this position gave the order to \u201cexpel the barbarians.\u201d The Jewel Voice Broadcast was delivered by the holder of this position. Between the 9th and 12th centuries, holders of this position frequently married women of the Fujiwara clan. In 1946, the holder of this position renounced his divine descent from the sun goddess Amaterasu. For ten points, name this position held by Hirohito during World War II.", "answer": "<b> Emperor of Japan</b> (accept word forms; prompt on partial answers, like \u201cemperor\u201d or \u201cleader of Japan\u201d)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "Natives who worked near this location were put on the silver roll as opposed to the gold roll, which was reserved for Americans and Europeans. John McCain was born in a U.S. administrative zone named for this location. The Torrijos-Carter Treaties specified a twenty year time frame for this location to pass from American control to that of a Central American country. For ten points, name this waterway, opened in 1914, that connects the Atlantic and Pacific Oceans.", "answer": "<b> Panama Canal</b> (accept<b> Panama Canal</b> Zone)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "In the aftermath of this event, Governor Kathleen Blanco emphasized that National Guardsmen were armed with M-16s and would \u201cshoot and kill.\u201d Two unarmed civilians were killed by police at Danziger Bridge after this disaster. Michael Brown was told he was \u201cdoing a heck of a job\u201d dealing with the devastation wrought by this event before he was fired from his post as Director of FEMA by George W. Bush. For ten points, name this 2005 natural disaster, a hurricane that devastated New Orleans and the Gulf Coast.", "answer": "Hurricane<b> Katrina</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This man advocated for a \u201cCommon European Home\u201d to prevent the threat of war from rival factions. This man, who removed Andrei Gromyko as foreign minister, began a policy of nonintervention known as the Sinatra Doctrine. The Gang of Eight targeted this man in a coup that was thwarted by a speech given atop a tank by Boris Yeltsin. The reforming policy of<em> glasnost</em> was championed by, for ten points, what final leader of the Soviet Union?", "answer": "Mikhail<b> Gorbachev</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Jedidiah Huntington led efforts to circumvent this law, which was succeeded by Macon\u2019s Bill No. 2 shortly after its repeal. In a famous cartoon criticizing its effects, a man carrying a barrel labeled \u201csuper fine\u201d attempts to break free of a snapping turtle\u2019s grasp. The \u201cOgrabme\u201d cartoon attacked, for ten points, what 1807 legislation enacted by Thomas Jefferson that was intended to block trade with Great Britain and France?", "answer": "<b> Embargo</b> Act of 1807", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Excavations at El-Haraneya showed that the most famous of these structures was linked by causeway to the Valley Temple. An early example of these structures consisted of six mastabas stacked upon each other; that building was built by Djoser and designed by the architect Imhotep. Examples of these structures commissioned by Menkaure, Khafre, and Khufu are found near the Sphinx. For ten points, identify these ancient Egyptian tombs.", "answer": "Egyptian<b> pyramid</b>s", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "After Reinhard Scheer led this force at an indecisive battle near the Skagerrak, Scheer recommended that this force loosen its restrictions on attacking without warning. This military force was dismantled at Scapa Flow on Ludwig von Reuter\u2019s orders, hoping that it would not be divided up between the victors after the Armistice. Alfred von Tirpitz revolutionized, for ten points, what military force that included the High Seas Fleet and which brought the US into World War I by sinking the<em> Lusitania</em>?", "answer": "Imperial<b> German Navy</b> (accept<b> High Seas Fleet</b> before mentioned; accept mentions of <b>German submarines</b> after \u201crestrictions\u201d is read; do not accept or prompt on mentions of Nazi Germany)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "Mike Pence, while serving as this state\u2019s governor, reluctantly backed some needle exchange programs in an attempt to stop the outbreak.", "answer": "<b> Indiana</b> <b></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b>This event prompted a message from John XXIII [23], in which he begged \u201call governments not to remain deaf to this cry of humanity.\u201d During this event, negotiations were mediated by U Thant, and Adlai Stevenson famously agitated for an (+) answer from</b> <b>Valerian Zorin. This event was ended with the removal of (*)</b> Jupiter weapon systems from Turkey, and it led to the creation of the Moscow-Washington hotline. For ten points, name this 1962 crisis in which the Soviet Union attempted to place weapons on a Caribbean island.", "answer": "<b> Cuban Missile Crisis</b> (accept<b> October Crisis</b>; accept descriptive answers of a diplomatic crisis regarding ballistic<b> missiles</b> placed in<b> Cuba</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>During this election year, Harold Stassen was told \u201cyou can\u2019t shoot an idea with a gun\u201dafter supporting a mandatory communist registry in this election year. Strom Thurmond</b> <b>ran on the breakaway (+)</b> <b>Dixiecrat ticket in this election year. In a famous photograph</b> <b>taken in this year, a man holds up an early edition of the (*)</b> Chicago Daily Tribune announcing the wrong outcome of the presidential election. For ten points, name this election year in which Thomas Dewey actually lost to Harry Truman, who thus earned a full second term in office.", "answer": "U.S. Presidential Election of<b> 1948</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>In a legend from this country, a woman who tries to ride her newlywed husband\u2019s horse</b> <b>is thrown off and bounces on her skirt all the way to the moon. Slue-Foot (+)</b> <b>Sue rode a</b> <b>catfish down a river in this country, and a man in this country dies after beating a steam powered hammer in a steel-driving contest. (*)</b> Pecos Bill and John Henry are two characters from the folklore of, for ten points, what country where Paul Bunyan\u2019s birth supposedly occurred in Wisconsin or Minnesota?", "answer": "<b> United States</b> of America (accept<b> US</b>A; accept<b> America</b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Film"}, {}, {"question": "<b>A polychoral style of music was developed in this city by Giovanni Gabrielli. This city was the final home of a composer who depicted the mistress of Nero in</b><em><b> The Coronation</b></em> <em><b>of Poppea</b></em><b>. Claudio Monteverdi worked in this city, where the (+)</b> <b>Ospedale della Piet`a</b> <b>employed the \u201cRed Priest\u201d who composed</b><em><b> The Four Seasons</b></em><b>. (*)</b> Antonio Vivaldi lived in, for ten points, what Italian city where opera was staged during Carnival and the barcarole was sung by gondoliers rowing along its canals?", "answer": "<b> Venice</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>James Habersham promoted slavery in this colony, whose original charter banned slavery and liquor. The southern border of this colony expanded to the Saint (+) Marys River after the English victory in the French and Indian War. For its first twenty years, this colony was governed by a Board of Trustees, who had initially intended it as a home for English (*)</b> debtors. James Oglethorpe founded, for ten points, what US colony that served as a southern buffer between the English colonies and Spanish Florida?", "answer": "<b> Georgia</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This region\u2019s Catholic nobles formed the Union of Green Mountain to contest George Podebrad\u2019s claim to this region\u2019s kingdom, which he contested with Hungarian King</b> <b>Matthias Corvinus. The House of Luxembourg ruled this kingdom under the (+)</b> <b>Blind</b> <b>King John, who died at the Battle of Crecy. In 1618, two Catholic regents were (*) </b>defenestrated in a city in this kingdom, helping trigger the Thirty Years\u2019 War. For ten points, name this region in the modern-day Czech Republic which, because French people in the 19th century believed the Romani came from this region, names an unattached artistic lifestyle.", "answer": "Kingdom of<b> Bohemia</b> (prompt on Czech Republic and/or Czechia before \u201cthis kingdom\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>A work dedicated to this man features friezes on which Ernest Bairstow carved the names of states. On the day that this man said \u201cLet us have faith that right makes might\u201d</b> <b>in the (+)</b> <b>Cooper Union speech, he was photographed at Mathew Brady\u2019s studio in New</b> <b>York. The Piccirilli brothers carved a sculpture of this man that had been designed by (*) </b>Daniel Chester French; that sculpture is the focus of a memorial at the west end of a reflecting pool on the National Mall. For ten points, name this American president whose memorial building in Washington, DC features inscriptions of the Gettysburg Address.", "answer": "Abraham<b> Lincoln</b> <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if you need a backup or tiebreaker!", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>This route was first trekked by the crew of the Tonquin and Wilson Price Hunt,</b> <b>who would go on to establish Fort Astoria here. This route branched off to Montana</b> <b>via the (+) Bozeman route and to Utah via the Mormon trail. One wagon route went</b> <b>as far as Fort (*)</b> Hall on this trail, which eventually stretched past the Cascade Mountains into the Willamette Valley. For ten points, name this 19th century trail that connected Missouri to the Pacific Northwest.", "answer": "<b> Oregon</b> Trail", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}